<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Tad Montgomery &amp; Associates</title>
	<atom:link href="./feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Ecological Engineer</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 13:19:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Rate of environmental degradation puts life on Earth at risk, say scientists</title>
		<link>/2015/01/16/rate-of-environmental-degradation-puts-life-on-earth-at-risk-say-scientists/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TadMontgomery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2015 01:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1156</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[&#8220;Humans are &#8216;eating away at our own life support systems&#8217; at a rate unseen in the past 10,000 years by degrading land and freshwater systems, emitting greenhouse gases and releasing vast amounts of agricultural chemicals into the environment, new research &#8230; <a href="./2015/01/16/rate-of-environmental-degradation-puts-life-on-earth-at-risk-say-scientists/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_1158" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="./wp-content/uploads/2015/01/Mojave-copy.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1158" decoding="async" class="size-medium wp-image-1158" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/Mojave-copy-300x188.jpg" alt="Sunburst over the Mojave Desert" width="300" height="188" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-1158" class="wp-caption-text">Sunburst over the Mojave Desert</p></div>
<p>&#8220;Humans are &#8216;eating away at our own life support systems&#8217; at a rate unseen in the past 10,000 years by degrading land and freshwater systems, emitting greenhouse gases and releasing vast amounts of agricultural chemicals into the environment, new research has found.&#8221;</p>
<p>This is from two studies, published in<a class=" u-underline" href="http://www.sciencemag.org/lookup/doi/10.1126/science.1259855" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="in-body-link"> Science</a> and <a class=" u-underline" href="http://anr.sagepub.com/" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="in-body-link">Anthropocene Review</a>.  An article on the studies can be found at <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/environment/2015/jan/15/rate-of-environmental-degradation-puts-life-on-earth-at-risk-say-scientists" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>The Guardian</em></a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Air Source Heat Pumps &#8212; Water Heating</title>
		<link>/2013/02/09/air-source-heat-pumps-water-heating/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TadMontgomery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2013 19:45:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Green & Natural Building]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[efficiency]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[water heaters]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=839</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[(This is an expanded version of an article published by Green Energy Times in their Dec. 2012 issue #17) If you have not heard the term ‘heat pump’ before, you will be soon.  Most people who are familiar with heat &#8230; <a href="./2013/02/09/air-source-heat-pumps-water-heating/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>(This is an expanded version of an article published by <a href="http://www.greenenergytimes.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Green Energy Times</a> in their Dec. 2012 issue #17)</em></p>
<p>If you have not heard the term ‘heat pump’ before, you will be soon.  Most people who are familiar with heat pumps associate them with ground-source or ‘geothermal’ systems that move heat from underground into a building using pumped water.  This article is about a much less familiar, less expensive and rapidly growing family of technologies called air source heat pumps (ASHP’s).</p>
<p>Heat pumps are actually quite common and include refrigerators and air conditioners.  They collect heat in one space and deliver it to another through the use of special fluids, a compressor and usually a fan.  The fluids are designed to evaporate within tubes in the space to be cooled, and condense in tubes in the space to be heated, all made possible through certain laws of thermodynamics.<span id="more-839"></span></p>
<p>ASHP’s take advantage of this engineering phenomenon to heat domestic hot water. Over the last few decades they have become very efficient devices that deliver two to three+ times more energy in heat than they consume in electricity.</p>
<div id="attachment_950" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="./wp-content/uploads/2013/02/ASHP-DHW-cutaway-copy.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-950" decoding="async" class="wp-image-950 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/ASHP-DHW-cutaway-copy-300x229.jpg" alt="ASHP DHW cutaway copy" width="300" height="229" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-950" class="wp-caption-text">Stiebel Eltron Accelera 300 Hot Water Heater</p></div>
<p>There are energy companies in Northern New England now who are replacing oil-fired boilers with ASHP’s for space and water heating. The ASHP water heater units are up to seven feet tall and look like a large electric water tank (see image).  They draw heat from the space where they are located and deliver it to the water in the tank, using just over one third of the energy of a standard electric water heater.  The total energy savings is much greater than this, however, because this swap allows a homeowner to turn off their home&#8217;s boiler in the warm months, eliminating the tremendous standby energy losses that happen when an oil boiler runs just to heat a building’s domestic hot water.  It has been estimated that an average homeowner can save 150-200 gallons of heating oil a year by replacing their oil boiler with an ASHP water heater.  At $3.85/gal. for heating oil and a price tag of $1,200 for a cheaper ASHP water heater, the payback period for such a conversion is less than two years.</p>
<p>Another substantial advantage of the ASHP hot water heaters is that they dehumidify the space where they are located.  If this space is a damp basement in which the homeowner often runs a dehumidifier in the summer, the energy efficiency of the whole ASHP system improves from &#8216;great&#8217; to &#8216;fantastic!&#8217;  As with all dehumidifiers, this will result in a water condensate that has to be dealt with.</p>
<p>There are a few disadvantages.  The ASHP water heaters can cost significantly more than conventional hot water systems.  ASHP’s for domestic hot water range from $1,200 to $2,500, but many utilities offer incentives up to $1,000 because of their amazing efficiency.  They are also said to be noisy, though the noise level, as well as the efficiency, varies substantially from unit to unit.  Another disadvantage is that an ASHP takes much longer to heat a tank of water than conventional water heaters do.  Because of this homeowners are often encouraged to buy the larger sized units, which cost more.  ASHP’s are also more complicated and have moving parts that can fail.  Different models also have different warrantees.</p>
<p>Air source heat pumps are not appropriate for every situation.  In the right setting, though, they have the potential to reduce energy usage dramatically.  These systems have been used in Asia and Europe for decades, and with energy prices consistently climbing in America we will be seeing a lot more of them here, too.  In fact, the federal government has all but mandated their use starting in 2015 by increasing the performance standards of water heaters.</p>
<p>In the future we expect these ASHP units to become even more efficient.  For example, warm outdoor air could be ducted to a water heater ASHP to increase its efficiency during warm months.  We can also envision an ASHP water heater being coupled with a refrigerator since they have opposite and complimentary thermal needs.  Likewise, waste ‘coolth’ from an ASHP water heater could be used in the summer to drop the temperature in a root cellar or for the cooling of living spaces.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Oyster Mushroom Cultivation</title>
		<link>/2012/10/14/oyster-mushroom-cultivation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TadMontgomery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 00:18:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Agroforestry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fungus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=833</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In 2012 I learned a new technique for oyster mushrooms from the folks at Field and Forest.  It&#8217;s done using large diameter logs cut into 6-8&#8243; lengths and stacked, with a &#8216;top plate&#8217; about 2&#8243; thick.  It&#8217;s called the &#8216;totem &#8230; <a href="./2012/10/14/oyster-mushroom-cultivation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1></h1>
<div id="attachment_958" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="./wp-content/uploads/2012/10/oyster-photo-2-2-copy.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-958" decoding="async" class="wp-image-958 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/oyster-photo-2-2-copy-300x225.jpg" alt="oyster photo 2 2 copy" width="300" height="225" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-958" class="wp-caption-text">Oyster Mushroom Totems in West Brattleboro</p></div>
<p>In 2012 I learned a new technique for oyster mushrooms from the folks at <a href="http://www.fieldforest.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Field and Forest</a>.  It&#8217;s done using large diameter logs cut into 6-8&#8243; lengths and stacked, with a &#8216;top plate&#8217; about 2&#8243; thick.  It&#8217;s called the &#8216;totem method.&#8217;  Spawn is layered between the rounds and the totem is kept moist, one way or another, for as long as possible.</p>
<p><span id="more-833"></span>I cut these rounds with the help of forester/logger Robert Spring in early spring, and inoculated and stacked them.  In October they started blooming.  So far I have sold batches to the Whetstone Station restaurant and brewery, and the Putney Food Coop.</p>
<p>Anyone who has cultivated mushrooms will tell you that different strains of the same mushroom can have very different characteristics.  This variety is called &#8216;grey dove&#8217; (<em>Pleurotus ostreatus</em>) and is known for being reliable, prolific, tasty and sturdy; all great characteristics for a culinary mushroom.  They do not keep nearly as well as other varieties of culinary mushroom, though, so it is important to harvest and get them to market quickly.</p>
<p>The more I work with fungus the more amazed I become with this kingdom of organisms.  There are varieties here in New England called Jack O&#8217;Lanterns that glow in the dark, and varieties in Oregon that grow under water in cold, fast flowing streams.  Oyster mushrooms are used to remediate toxic waste that is organic in composition, such as petrochemicals.  See my page on remediation for more on this.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Air Source Heat Pumps &#8212; Space Heating</title>
		<link>/2012/10/14/air-source-heat-pumps-space-heating/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TadMontgomery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2012 21:42:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Energy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Green & Natural Building]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Home]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[space heating]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=825</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[(This is an expanded version of an article published by &#8216;Green Energy Times&#8217; in their Oct. 2012 issue, #16) By Tad Montgomery Most people either have not heard of an air source heat pump (ASHP) or do not know how &#8230; <a href="./2012/10/14/air-source-heat-pumps-space-heating/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>(This is an expanded version of an article published by &#8216;<a href="http://www.greenenergytimes.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Green Energy Times&#8217;</a> in their</em> <em>Oct. 2012 issue, #16)</em></p>
<p>By Tad Montgomery</p>
<div id="attachment_952" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="./wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Rosenbaum-HP-Outside.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-952" decoding="async" class="wp-image-952 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Rosenbaum-HP-Outside-300x225.jpg" alt="Rosenbaum HP Outside" width="300" height="225" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-952" class="wp-caption-text">Marc Rosenbaum&#8217;s Fujitsu 12RLS single zone ductless &#8216;mini-split&#8217; heat pump (energysmiths.com)</p></div>
<p>Most people either have not heard of an air source heat pump (ASHP) or do not know how common they are. Most of us own one or more already, because they include nearly all refrigerators and air conditioners.</p>
<p><span id="more-825"></span>ASHPs collect heat in one space and deliver it to another through the use of special fluids, a compressor, and usually a fan. The fluids evaporate within tubes in the space to be cooled, and condense in tubes in a space to be heated. We might transfer heat from a house to the outdoors, or the other way around. We also might transfer heat from one part of a house to another in the same way.</p>
<p>The ASHP known as a ductless mini-split is an excellent example. The mini-split is not very large, hence &#8216;mini,&#8217; but it is also divided into two or more components, with a compressor in one place and condensers or evaporators in up to four other places, hence &#8216;split&#8217;. They can serve both as heaters and air conditioners.</p>
<p>The mini-splits have become very efficient devices that deliver two to three+ times more energy in heat than they consume in electricity. Though this might sound like a violation of the laws of physics, they achieve this because the heat is being moved, rather than produced directly from electricity.</p>
<p>A single compressor for an ASHP, usually placed outdoors, might supply heating and/or cooling to as many as four places in the house. This is where the ductless part comes in.  Ducts are often among the worst problems with regard to a building&#8217;s energy efficiency. The ductless mini-split moves liquids instead of gases, and only a short distance.  That is part of the reason why it is so efficient.</p>
<p>There are, of course, down sides. The mini-splits have a minimum temperature rating, dependent on model, and if the outdoor temperature drops below it the heating system switches to conventional electric resistance heating or a backup heating system is required. This minimum temperature varies from unit to unit and can be as low as -10°F. Different models also have different warranties.</p>
<p>Air source heat pumps are not appropriate for every situation. One example is trying to heat a leaky, old Victorian house with an ASHP.  One client of mine wanted this until she learned that five units would be needed at a cost of $25,000.  The first step in such a situation is almost always to button up and insulate, then explore alternative heating systems.</p>
<p>In the right situation mini-splits have the potential to reduce energy usage dramatically while increasing comfort. These systems have been used in Asia and Europe for decades, and now that energy prices are climbing in America we will be seeing a lot more of them here, too.</p>
<div id="attachment_951" style="width: 197px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="./wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Rosenbaum-HP-Indoor.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-951" decoding="async" class="wp-image-951 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/Rosenbaum-HP-Indoor-187x300.jpg" alt="Rosenbaum HP Indoor" width="187" height="300" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-951" class="wp-caption-text">Interior component of Rosenbaum&#8217;s Fujitsu mini-split (above painting)</p></div>
<p>Marc Rosenbaum of Energysmiths installed a mini-split in his 1,600 sq. ft. house on Martha’s Vineyard in 2012 to replace a high efficiency boiler (see photos). He has monitored the system extensively and reports that he reduced his heating energy consumption by 75%. His plan is to install photovoltaic panels at his house in order to cut his reliance on nuclear and fossil fuel. He also installed an ASHP hot water heater, but that will be the subject of a later article.</p>
<p>In the future we expect these ASHP units to become even more efficient. For example, some commercial applications of mini-splits capture heat in one area of a building where cooling is needed and bring that heat to another area where it is needed for space heating.</p>
<p><strong>Rebates: </strong>Efficiency Vermont &amp; PSNH sporadically offer rebates for ASHP’s.  A representative for PSHN queried by <em>Green Energy Times</em> emailed: “For 2013-2014, all 4 (NH) electric utilities proposed heating and cooling system rebates, including a rebate for mini-split / air source heat pumps. We think this technology is extremely efficient and works great with homes heated by Oil or LP FHW (liquid propane forced hot water – eds).” The NH Electric Co-Op offers rebates up to $2,000 for mini-splits. Western Mass. Electric $150-500 for “Central AC/Heat Pump.”  For up-to-date information on rebates and incentives contact <a title="Home Energy Advocates" href="http://www/HomeEnergyAdvocates.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Home Energy Advocates</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Models: </strong>Two ASHP space heater models are Mitsubishi’s ‘Mr. Slim’ and the Fujitsu 12RLS.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Inspiring School Biofuel Project</title>
		<link>/2012/09/04/inspiring-school-biofuel-project/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TadMontgomery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Sep 2012 15:53:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biofuels]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Energy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=816</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here&#8217;s a wonderful TED Talk video of a student project on biofuels: httpv://youtu.be/Q05Ie4b89Yw They started without even the benefit of an idea, just an intention.  Through a beautiful process of dialog, building allies and collaboration they enlisted restaurants, grease collectors, &#8230; <a href="./2012/09/04/inspiring-school-biofuel-project/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #888888;"><a href="./wp-content/uploads/2012/09/Soybeanbus-copy.jpg"><img decoding="async" class=" size-thumbnail wp-image-963 alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/Soybeanbus-copy-150x97.jpg" alt="Soybeanbus copy" width="150" height="97" /></a>Here&#8217;s a wonderful TED Talk video of a student project on biofuels:</span></p>
<p>httpv://youtu.be/Q05Ie4b89Yw</p>
<p><span style="color: #888888;">They started without even the benefit of an idea, just an intention.  Through a beautiful process of dialog, building allies and collaboration they enlisted restaurants, grease collectors, a biofuel producer, scientists, legislators, fuel distributors, and organizations dedicated to helping the poor and came up with a very inspiring project.  I can&#8217;t help but wonder how that kind of vision and self-confidence could be engendered in every high school student.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cargo Bicycles</title>
		<link>/2012/08/31/cargo-bicycles/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TadMontgomery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2012 01:58:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Transportation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=810</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here&#8217;s the future of everyday people getting into bicycling.  It&#8217;s beautiful.  Dave Cohen is a psychologist here in Brattleboro with a strong inclination towards connecting people with nature.  We had lunch today and talked about his work pushing the culture &#8230; <a href="./2012/08/31/cargo-bicycles/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #888888;">Here&#8217;s the future of everyday people getting into bicycling.  It&#8217;s beautiful.  Dave Cohen is a psychologist here in Brattleboro with a strong inclination towards connecting people with nature.  We had lunch today and talked about his work pushing the culture shift towards bicycles, especially electrical assist cargo bicycles.  He ran a cargo bike transport business in Berkeley for a bunch of years and has recently gotten Burrows Specialized Sports here in town to carry the <a href="http://yubaride.com/mundo-cargo-bike">Yuba Cargo Bikes</a>.  Later in the day he sent me this video link.<br />
</span></p>
<p>httpv://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lM_FYVmaZTc</p>
<p><span style="color: #888888;">I&#8217;ve recently been blessed with a new custom bike</span> <span style="color: #888888;">that was pulled together very gracefully by local mechanic Nik Perry, but more on that on another post.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Living Bridges of India</title>
		<link>/2012/08/22/the-living-bridges-of-india/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TadMontgomery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2012 00:42:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ecological Design]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Green & Natural Building]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[plants]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=687</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the depths of northeastern India, in one of the world&#8217;s wettest places, bridges aren&#8217;t built &#8212; they&#8217;re grown. Video Imagine working with your daughter or son, maybe your grandchildren, to build something that will last 50 generations?]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #808080;"><a href="./wp-content/uploads/2012/08/Living-Bridge.jpg"><img decoding="async" class=" wp-image-965 size-medium alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/Living-Bridge-300x200.jpg" alt="Living Bridge" width="300" height="200" /></a>In the depths of northeastern India, in one of the world&#8217;s wettest places, bridges aren&#8217;t built &#8212; they&#8217;re grown.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #808080;"><span style="color: #0000ff;"><a href="http://atlasobscura.com/place/root-bridges-cherrapungee"><span style="color: #0000ff;">Video</span></a></span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #888888;">Imagine working with your daughter or son, maybe your grandchildren, to build something that will last 50 generations?</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The End of Peak Oil?</title>
		<link>/2012/08/18/the-end-of-peak-oil/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TadMontgomery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 18 Aug 2012 23:03:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ecological Engineering]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Energy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Climate Change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Peak Oil]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=675</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Alex Wilson of Building Green has recently written an opinion piece disputing the urgency of peak oil.  He believes that all of the new discoveries of oil reserves, from offshore Brazilian fields to recent discoveries in North Dakota, combined with &#8230; <a href="./2012/08/18/the-end-of-peak-oil/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #808080;"><a href="./wp-content/uploads/2012/08/Building-Green-logo.jpg"><img decoding="async" class="alignleft wp-image-968 size-medium" src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/Building-Green-logo-300x65.jpg" alt="Building Green logo" width="300" height="65" /></a>Alex Wilson of Building Green has recently written an <a href="http://www2.buildinggreen.com/blogs/end-peak-oil">opinion piece</a> disputing the urgency of peak oil.  He believes that all of the new discoveries of oil reserves, from offshore Brazilian fields to recent discoveries in North Dakota, combined with new &#8216;fracking&#8217; technologies that squeeze more oil from existing fields, have pushed back peak oil by decades, at least.  This is good news for all of those who, with some justification, believed that we were on the precipice of a civilizational collapse with the end of oil.  It is bad news from the perspective of climate change.  We at TM&amp;A have felt that peak oil was overblown for some time, both for the reasons that Wilson documents in his article but also because of energy technologies that we know to be feasible which could dramatically reduce our reliance on fossil fuels.  The Energy Amplifier is just one such technology, described in some detail under the Energy section of this website.  </span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lifecycle Effects of Biodiesel</title>
		<link>/2012/08/09/lifecycle-effects-of-biodiesel/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TadMontgomery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2012 18:18:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biofuels]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Climate Change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biodiesel]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=484</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[According to the EPA&#8217;s Renewable Fuel Standards Program Regulatory Impact Analysis, released in February 2010, biodiesel from soy oil results, on average, in a 57% reduction in greenhouse gases compared to petroleum diesel, and biodiesel produced from waste grease results &#8230; <a href="./2012/08/09/lifecycle-effects-of-biodiesel/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="./wp-content/uploads/2012/09/Soybeanbus-copy.jpg"><img decoding="async" class="alignleft wp-image-963 size-thumbnail" title="Soybean bus" src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/Soybeanbus-copy-150x97.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="97" /></a><br />
<span style="color: #888888;">According to the EPA&#8217;s <a href="http://www.epa.gov/otaq/renewablefuels/420r10006.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Renewable Fuel Standards Program Regulatory Impact Analysis</a>, released in February 2010, biodiesel from soy oil results, on average, in a 57% reduction in greenhouse gases compared to petroleum diesel, and biodiesel produced from waste grease results in an 86% reduction. See chapter 2.6 of the EPA report for more detailed information.</span><span id="more-484"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #888888;">One particularly interesting point that the report makes concerning tailpipe emissions of powerful greenhouse gasses is the following: &#8220;For diesel highway vehicles, emissions of N2O and CH4 are almost one hundred times less than emissions from gasoline vehicles &#8230;&#8221; (pg. 493). CH4 has a GHG rating of 21 times worse than CO2, and N2O has a rating of 310. Unfortunately, they do not seem to take into account NOx&#8217;s: NO2 &amp; NO3 which, while nowhere near as potent as N2O, are still many times more potent than carbon dioxide as a greenhouse gas and are reported to be produced more in diesel engines due to the higher temperatures of operation.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #888888;">Based on this comprehensive report is can be assumed that biofuel applications that use waste vegetable oil directly, without chemical processing, result in a greenhouse gas reduction of 90-95%. This is not only due to the lack of methanol and sodium hydroxide inputs, but also because much waste vegetable oil is still thrown away by small producers and has the likely potential to end up in a landfill, decomposing anaerobically and releasing methane, a potent greenhouse gas.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Maitake Mushroom Inoculation</title>
		<link>/2012/08/07/maitake-mushroom-inoculation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TadMontgomery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2012 02:17:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Agroforestry]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fungus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Grifola frondosa]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[hen of the woods]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maitake]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[medicinal]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=404</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It&#8217;s high summer, and a good time to inoculate hardwood trees with edible and medicinal mushrooms.  Lately we have been focused on maitake, or &#8216;hen of the woods&#8217; mushrooms in and around Brattleboro.  This is part of an agro-forestry initiative &#8230; <a href="./2012/08/07/maitake-mushroom-inoculation/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="./wp-content/uploads/2012/08/Grifola_frondosa_at_base_of_oak_tree.jpg"><img decoding="async" class="  alignleft wp-image-972 size-medium" title="800px-Many_Grifola_frondosa_at_the_base_of_an_oak_tree" src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/Grifola_frondosa_at_base_of_oak_tree-300x225.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="225" /></a></p>
<p><span style="color: #888888;">It&#8217;s high summer, and a good time to inoculate hardwood trees with edible and medicinal mushrooms.  Lately we have been focused on maitake, or &#8216;hen of the woods&#8217; mushrooms in and around Brattleboro.  This is part of an agro-forestry initiative that we have been engaged in, developing value-added forestry crops.  Maitake have both tremendous culinary value and have been shown to provide substantial health benefits as well with research showing that they boost the immune system and help to combat cancer.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
