<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Biofuels &#8211; Tad Montgomery &amp; Associates</title>
	<atom:link href="./category/biofuels/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Ecological Engineer</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 13:19:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Inspiring School Biofuel Project</title>
		<link>/2012/09/04/inspiring-school-biofuel-project/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TadMontgomery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Sep 2012 15:53:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biofuels]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Energy]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=816</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Here&#8217;s a wonderful TED Talk video of a student project on biofuels: httpv://youtu.be/Q05Ie4b89Yw They started without even the benefit of an idea, just an intention.  Through a beautiful process of dialog, building allies and collaboration they enlisted restaurants, grease collectors, &#8230; <a href="./2012/09/04/inspiring-school-biofuel-project/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="color: #888888;"><a href="./wp-content/uploads/2012/09/Soybeanbus-copy.jpg"><img decoding="async" class=" size-thumbnail wp-image-963 alignright" src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/Soybeanbus-copy-150x97.jpg" alt="Soybeanbus copy" width="150" height="97" /></a>Here&#8217;s a wonderful TED Talk video of a student project on biofuels:</span></p>
<p>httpv://youtu.be/Q05Ie4b89Yw</p>
<p><span style="color: #888888;">They started without even the benefit of an idea, just an intention.  Through a beautiful process of dialog, building allies and collaboration they enlisted restaurants, grease collectors, a biofuel producer, scientists, legislators, fuel distributors, and organizations dedicated to helping the poor and came up with a very inspiring project.  I can&#8217;t help but wonder how that kind of vision and self-confidence could be engendered in every high school student.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lifecycle Effects of Biodiesel</title>
		<link>/2012/08/09/lifecycle-effects-of-biodiesel/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[TadMontgomery]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2012 18:18:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biofuels]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Global Climate Change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[biodiesel]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=484</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[According to the EPA&#8217;s Renewable Fuel Standards Program Regulatory Impact Analysis, released in February 2010, biodiesel from soy oil results, on average, in a 57% reduction in greenhouse gases compared to petroleum diesel, and biodiesel produced from waste grease results &#8230; <a href="./2012/08/09/lifecycle-effects-of-biodiesel/">Continue reading <span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="./wp-content/uploads/2012/09/Soybeanbus-copy.jpg"><img decoding="async" class="alignleft wp-image-963 size-thumbnail" title="Soybean bus" src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/09/Soybeanbus-copy-150x97.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="97" /></a><br />
<span style="color: #888888;">According to the EPA&#8217;s <a href="http://www.epa.gov/otaq/renewablefuels/420r10006.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Renewable Fuel Standards Program Regulatory Impact Analysis</a>, released in February 2010, biodiesel from soy oil results, on average, in a 57% reduction in greenhouse gases compared to petroleum diesel, and biodiesel produced from waste grease results in an 86% reduction. See chapter 2.6 of the EPA report for more detailed information.</span><span id="more-484"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #888888;">One particularly interesting point that the report makes concerning tailpipe emissions of powerful greenhouse gasses is the following: &#8220;For diesel highway vehicles, emissions of N2O and CH4 are almost one hundred times less than emissions from gasoline vehicles &#8230;&#8221; (pg. 493). CH4 has a GHG rating of 21 times worse than CO2, and N2O has a rating of 310. Unfortunately, they do not seem to take into account NOx&#8217;s: NO2 &amp; NO3 which, while nowhere near as potent as N2O, are still many times more potent than carbon dioxide as a greenhouse gas and are reported to be produced more in diesel engines due to the higher temperatures of operation.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #888888;">Based on this comprehensive report is can be assumed that biofuel applications that use waste vegetable oil directly, without chemical processing, result in a greenhouse gas reduction of 90-95%. This is not only due to the lack of methanol and sodium hydroxide inputs, but also because much waste vegetable oil is still thrown away by small producers and has the likely potential to end up in a landfill, decomposing anaerobically and releasing methane, a potent greenhouse gas.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
